Preliminary Guide to the Lenora Greenbaum Ucko papers, 1966-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Lenora Greenbaum Ucko papers 1966-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Ucko, Leonora Greenbaum
7.0 Linear Feet 4220 Items
Professor of anthropology, sociology, and social work, who founded StoriesWork, a non-profit organization in Durham, N.C. that advocates Therapeutic Storytelling, or the use of folk story analysis for empowering abused women.
Collection consists of several separate accessions and includes Ucko's travel diaries; teaching and course materials; transcripts of Ucko's publications, including her book, Endangered Spouses; correspondence; Russian genalogy; materials from the Henry Zvi Ucko Memorial Exhibit, "What We Brought with Us," which featured personal items taken by German Jews who fled Nazi Germany in the 1930s; and other materials from Ucko's position at the Museum of the Jewish Family in the late 1990s. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
In addition, patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lenora Greenbaum Ucko papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006, 2007, and 2011.
Biographical Note
Professor of anthropology, sociology, and social work. Founded StoriesWork, a non-profit organization in Durham, N.C., advocating Therapeutic Storytelling, or the use of folk story analysis for empowering abused women. The organization offers training to domestic violence staff/volunteers, the medical/psychiatric profession; the legal profession and private practitioners.
Collection Overview
Accession (2006-0015) consists primarily of files, lectures, and papers for classes taught by Ucko; files pertaining to cross-cultural communications prepared for the U.S. Army JFK Special Warfare Center; 20 labeled color slides; and travel diaries from Sierra Leone, Cuba, the Dominican Republic, Egypt, Senegal, Pakistan, and Holland.
Addition (2007-0015) (750 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1973-1994) contains typescripts and promotional material for articles and books including Endangered Spouses; course materials including files, papers, and class rosters; correspondence; and one audiocassette. Also included are materials from a study of Russian genealogy by students at Aldephi University directed by Ucko.
Addition (2007-0066) (200 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1996-1998) contains slides, photographs, oral histories on audiocassettes, 1 VHS videocassettes, printed and other materials all concerning a 1996 exhibit Lenora Ucko curated in honor of her late husband, Henry Zvi Ucko. The exhibit was entitled What We Brought with Us, an exhibit about the personal items taken by German Jews who fled Nazi Germany in the 1930s. The exhibit was first at Duke University and then moved to the NC Museum of History in Raleigh.
Addition (2011-0063) (900 items, 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1994-2002) largely consists of materials from Ucko's involvement in the Museum of the Jewish Family. Museum materials include programming pamphlets and advertising, exhibitions, budget materials, grant applications, Board of Directors correspondence and meeting minutes, newsletters, mission and by-laws, and other materials from the operation of the organization, primarily dated 1997-1998. Other items in this addition include some of Ucko's correspondence, her research on museums and memory, and some StoriesWork materials.
Addition (2013-0052) (75 items; .1 lin. ft.; dated 1975, 1981-1982, 2004, 2006, 2008-2009, 2013) includes a research paper and notes on Israeli absorption centers as well as newsletters and pamphlets for StoriesWork. Other items in this addition include pamphlets and flyers advertising Ucko's research consulting business, a program for a 1975 production of All in the Family at the University of Maryland Munich campus (Ucko served as faculty advisor), and a 2013 resume.
The Lenora Greenbaum Ucko Papers were acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Ucko, Lenora Greenbaum
Genealogy
Jews -- Germany -- 1930-1940
Marriage -- Folklore
Anthropology
Photographs
Audiocassettes
Videocassettes
Slides
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2006-0015), 6 Boxes
  Accession consists primarily of files, lectures, and papers for classes taught by Ucko; files pertaining to cross-cultural communications prepared for the U.S. Army JFK Special Warfare Center; 20 labeled color slides; and travel diaries from Sierra Leone, Cuba, the Dominican Republic, Egypt, Senegal, Pakistan, and Holland.
  - Professional correspondence (Box 1)
  - Dr. Greenbaum's dissertation (Box 1)
  - Yale University summer seminar information (Box 1)
  - Research notes (Box 1)
  - Academic research papers (Box 1)
  - Academic research papers (Box 2)
  - Cross-cultural communication lesson plans (Box 2)
  - University course material (Box 3)
  - East Asia tradition (Box 3)
  - Middle East traditions (Box 3)
  - Dissertation material (Box 3)
  - Course material for courses taught by Dr. Ucko at Duke University (Box 3)
  - Love and Marriage mythology (Box 4)
  - Culture and Violence (Box 4)
  - Academic papers (Box 4)
  - Who's on top (Box 5)
  - Travel information (Box 5)
  - Dominican Republic Diary (Box 5)
  - Notebooks (Box 5)
  - European Women (Box 6)
  - Senegal research diary (Box 6)
  - Pakistan diary (Box 6)
- Accession (2007-0015), 2 Boxes
  Addition (750 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1973-1994) contains typescripts and promotional material for articles and books including Endangered Spouses; course materials including files, papers, and class rosters; correspondence; and one audiocassette. Also included are materials from a study of Russian genealogy by students at Aldephi University directed by Ucko.
  - Typescripts and publicity materials for Endangered Spouses (Box 7)
  - Typescripts for other articles (Box 7)
  - Teaching files (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1992 (Box 7)
  - Typescripts for articles and a short play, Shalom Bayit (Box 8)
  - Student papers (Box 8)
  - Teaching materials (Box 8)
  - Materials for Russian genealogy studies (Box 8)
  - Audiocassette (Box 8)
- Accession (2007-0066), 1 Box
  Addition (200 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1996-1998) contains slides, photographs, oral histories on audiocassettes, 1 VHS videotape, printed and other materials all concerning a 1996 exhibit Lenora Ucko curated in honor of her late husband, Henry Zvi Ucko. The exhibit was entitled What We Brought with Us, an exhibit about the personal items taken by German Jews who fled Nazi Germany in the 1930s. The exhibit was first at Duke University and then moved to the NC Museum of History in Raleigh.
  - What We Brought with Us exhibit materials (Box 9)
    - Videocassette of Leonora Ucko public reception, Duke University Library, October 19, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Oral histories, (15 audiocassettes) (Box 9)
    - Photographs of exhibit materials (Box 9)
    - Slides, (12 items) (Box 9)
    - Printed materials (Box 9)
- Accession (2011-0063), (1 box)
  Addition (2011-0063) (900 items, 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1994-2002) largely consists of materials from Ucko's involvement in the Museum of the Jewish Family. Museum materials include programming pamphlets and advertising, exhibitions, budget materials, grant applications, Board of Directors correspondence and meeting minutes, newsletters, mission and by-laws, and other materials from the operation of the organization, primarily dated 1997-1998. Other items in this addition include some of Ucko's correspondence, her research on museums and memory, and some StoriesWork materials.
  - Correspondence, 1993-1998 (Box 10)
  - Museum of the Jewish Family materials, (17 folders) (Box 10)
    Programming pamphlets and advertising, budget materials, grant applications, Board of Directors correspondence and meeting minutes, newsletters, mission and by-laws, and other materials from the operation of the organization, primarily dated 1997-1998. Includes coverage of the exhibit "What We Brought With Us." Also includes early inventories of the Rosenzweig Collection. Particular exhibitions or programming are detailed below.
    - Artist, Bible, and Storyteller program, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Ala Moses sculpture (Box 10)
    - From Russia With Love exhibit (Box 10)
    - Rattner exhibit (Box 10)
    - Jewish-Arab Cross Cultural Encounters, 1995 (Box 10)
    - Meaning of Light in Jewish Tradition, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Jewish Film Festival exhibitions, 1999 (Box 10)
    - Kanof Israeli Medals exhibit, 1994, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Light is for Everyone, 1997-1998 (Box 10)
    - The Running Stag: Images of Israel in Postage Stamp Art, 1998, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - Migrations: Jewish Settlers of Eastern North Carolina, 1998-1999, (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - Articles written by Ucko (Box 10)
  - Stories workshop evaluations (Box 10)
  - StoriesWork promotion/publicity (Box 10)
  - Ucko's research (Box 10)
    - Holocaust (Box 10)
    - Jewish fabric and handicrafts (Box 10)
    - Museum/curatorship articles (Box 10)
    - Memory articles (Box 10)
  - Association of Jewish Libraries (Box 10)
  - Council of American Jewish Museums (Box 10)
  - Beth Shalom Centre, England, (2 folders) (Box 10)
- Accession (2013-0052), (2 folders)
  Addition (2013-0052) (75 items; .1 lin. ft.; dated 1975, 1981-1982, 2004, 2006, 2008-2009, 2013) includes a research paper and notes on Israeli absorption centers as well as newsletters and pamphlets for StoriesWork. Other items in this addition include pamphlets and flyers advertising Ucko's research consulting business, a program for a 1975 production of All in the Family at the University of Maryland Munich campus (Ucko served as faculty advisor), and a 2013 resume.
  - Israeli Absorption Centers1981-1982 (Box 10)
  - StoriesWork, research consulting, All in the Family, resume (Box 10)